As for this marriage
혼사라는 건
It mainly depends on fate
인연을 봐야 해
Have that girl called
완아라는 아이의
Wan'er
사주단자를
Have her birth characters
예부에 보내
Sent to the Ministry of Rites for calculation
궁합이 맞는지
To see if they match
맞춰보거라
Thank you, Your Majesty, thank you, Father
성은이 망극하옵니다
Enough
됐네
All dismissed
모두 물러가게
This marriage
문무백관 앞에서
Was requested before all the court officials
주청을 올린 혼사라
Once it's settled
일단 정해지면
It means
영왕과 진가의
Your Majesty has tacitly approved
관계가 더 깊어지는 걸
Prince of Ning and the Chen family further bound together
폐하께서 묵인한 셈이에요
Once they gain momentum
그쪽으로 대세가 기울면
Those who are watching
관망하던 사람들도
Will gradually align with Prince of Ning
다 영왕 편에 설 겁니다
Your subject has also learned
그리고 제가 알아본 바로
General Zu Kun from the north
북쪽 조곤 장군이
Is about to return to court to report
조정에 돌아와 복명하는데요
It's said
듣자하니
The vanguard troops
선봉대가 이미
Have already camped outside the city
교외에 주둔했답니다
The Zu family
조씨는
Has always been neutral
늘 중립을 지켰어요
If
만일
At this time
이때 호도되어
They are swayed
한쪽으로 기울면
Then
정말
It would be terrible
큰일 아닙니까
Though the marriage is small
혼사는
Its implications are great
큰일이 아니지만
Your Majesty ordered the Ministry of Rites to check compatibility
파급력이 아주 커요
Likely wants to reconsider
아직 생각 중이실 테니
Your Highness
전하
We must find a way
어떻게든 이 혼사를
To ruin this marriage
훼방 놓아야 합니다
I understand
알겠습니다
This old minister
제가
Will visit various parties again
사람들을 만나보며
And think of other solutions
바른 방도를 생각해 볼게요
Mother
모후
Your son has made many arrangements
소자가 여러모로 많이 준비했습니다
Your son Sikong Yao
소자 사공요
Pays respects to Mother
모후께 문안 올립니다
Yao'er is here
요아가 왔구나
Second brother
둘째야
Quick
얼른
Quick, let Yao'er come in
얼른 들라 해라
Elder brother is here too
형님도 계셨네요
Second brother
둘째야
Haven't visited Mother in so long
너 모후 뵈러 오랜만에 왔지
Hurry and apologize to Mother
얼른 모후께 큰절 올리며
By kowtowing
사죄하거라
Mother
모후
Your son is not in the palace
소자 궁을 나간 이래
And hasn't visited often
자주 뵈러 오지도 못했어요
Please forgive me, Mother
용서해 주십시오
Alright, alright
됐어
That you came to see me
이렇게 보러 온 것만 해도
Makes me very happy
아주 기쁘구나
Today is truly a joyous day
오늘은 좋은 날이야
My Zheng'er
우리 정아랑
And Yao'er
요아가
Have both come to visit me
다 날 보러 왔어
Xiaoqing
소청아
Go get the pastry boxes
내가 얼마 전에 만든
I made the other day
다과를 가져오너라
What's wrong?
왜 그러느냐
Your Majesty
황후마마
You previously gave the pastries to us servants
그 다과는 저희에게 하사하셔서
Now only one remains
지금 한 개밖에 남지 않았어요
Oh, my memory
내 정신 좀 봐
Making them now
지금 하기엔
Is too late
너무 늦었고